Frederick T. Volk Papers
Frederick T. Volk Papers
1861-1867
Volk, Frederick T.
0.5 linear ft.
Papers of the Union soldier. Officer in Company B, 65th New York Volunteers. Documents of Company B, 65th New York Volunteers (1864-1865), including invoices, muster rolls, ordnance stores inventories and records of clothing allowances, and receipts; diary (1864-1865); and other personal papers (1861-1867).
148721
Biographical History
Frederick T. Volk, a native of New York City, was a sailor before serving in the Union army during the Civil War. Mustered-in as a private in 1861, he progressed through the ranks, achieving a commission as captain of Company B, Sixty-fifth New York Volunteers, by 1864. Volk participated in the Battle of the Wilderness during Grant's campaign against Richmond in 1864 and was wounded in the Spotsylvania Court House action of the same campaign. Ordered to officers' hospitals in Philadelphia and then Annapolis for recuperation, Volk returned to the front lines in November 1864 and was active in the siege of Petersburg.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Frederick T. Volk Papers contain both military documents and personal papers of a Union army officer. The 112 items date from 1861 to 1867.
Company documents are of Company B, Sixty-fifth New York Volunteers, date from 1864 to 1865, during Volk's captaincy. There are clothing, camp and garrison equipage returns, muster rolls, ordnance stores, and statements of clothing allowance, arranged in that order. Clothing, camp and garrison equipage returns are abstracts of the expenditures of equipment during battle or while on march. Included with a statement of the cost of clothing, camp and garrison equipage is a table of money values. Two folders of muster rolls show enlistments, substitutions, discharges, sick leaves, deaths, and desertions, also noting duration of service and remarking on discipline, instruction, military appearance, arms, accoutrements, and clothing. Muster-out rolls are individualized records of service for soldiers separated from the service. The ordnance stores include reports of ordnance lost or destroyed and records of the receipt and dispersal of ordnance supplies. Statements of clothing allowance record the receipt of articles of clothing by noncommissioned officers, artificers, musicians, and privates of Company B.
Personal papers also date primarily from Volk's service in the Civil War. A black, leather-encased pocket diary, 1864-1865, contains notes jotted down just prior to and during Grant's campaign against Richmond, covers his service as captain in Company B, and records his impressions and varied experiences at the Battle of the Wilderness, the Battle of Spotsylvania Court House, the siege of Petersburg (all 1864), and his convalescence at officers' hospitals in Philadelphia and Annapolis. Promotions and commendations include enlistment certificates, documents of appointment to higher rank, and records of commendation. Muster-in and muster-out rolls document Volk's promotions from second lieutenant to captain of Company B. The special orders consist of ordinances received by Volk as captain of Company B, and recommendations on their application under war-time conditions. Voucher certificates are records of indebtedness or accountability to the United States by Volk upon separation from service. Further details on holdings are given in the shelf-list.
Arrangement of the Collection
Material is arranged in alphabetical order within each series.
Related Material
has numerous collections relating to military history and to the U.S. Civil War. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; Civil War (U.S.); Volk, Frederick T.; United States. -- Army -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Sources.; United States. -- Army -- Officers.; United States. -- Army -- Ordnance and ordnance stores.; United States. -- Army. -- New York Infantry Regiment, 65th (1861-1865); Soldiers -- United States.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Equipment and supplies.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Sources.; United States -- History -- Military -- To 1900 -- Sources.; Diaries.; Inventories.; Invoices.; Muster rolls.; Receipts (financial records); Soldiers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 1963.
Inventory
- Company documents
  - Clothing, camp, and garrison equipage returns, 1864-1865 (Box 1)
  - Muster rolls, June 30, 1864-June 25, 1865; 8 items (Box 1)
  - Muster-out rolls, February, May and June 1865; 6 items (Box 1)
  - Ordnance stores
    - Inventory and inspection reports, April 29, 1864; March 3, 1865;; June 24, 1865 (Box 1)
    - Invoices of stores, November 1864-July 1865 (Box 1)
    - Issues and transfers, December 1864-July 1865; undated (Box 1)
    - Lost or destroyed, April-June 1865; undated (Box 1)
    - Quarterly returns, 1864-1865 (Box 1)
    - Shipments received, April 1864; November 1864-July 1865 (Box 1)
  - Statements of clothing allowances, 1864-1865 (Box 1)
- Personal papers
  - Diary, 1864-1865 (Box 1)
  - Hospital bills, May-Oct, 1864 (Box 1)
  - Muster-in and muster-out rolls, July 1863; December 1863,; November 1864 (Box 1)
  - Promotions and commendations, 1861-1863; 1865-1866 (Box 1)
  - Special orders, May 1864-June 1865 (Box 1)
  - Voucher certificates, 1864; 1867 (Box 1)